Finding aid to the Helen Gurley Brown papers SSC.MS.00022
Sophia Smith Collection
- SERIES IV. WRITINGS, (1940; 1956-2000)
  - Newspaper columns
    - "Woman Alone" (syndicated column), 1963-65
      - Correspondence (includes financial material), 1962-65 (Box 31, Folder 11)
      - Typescripts and articles
        - Apr-Sep 1963 (Box 31, Folder 12)
        - Sep 1963-Apr 1965 (Box 32, Folder 1-5)
      - Miscellaneous typescripts and clippings of columns (Box 32, Folder 6)
      - Ads and clippings about, 1963-65 (Box 32, Folder 7)
    - Outrageous Opinions (book compiled from column), 1966 (Box 32, Folder 8)
  - Phonograph albums
    - Clippings, 1962; 1966 (Box 33, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence (includes royalty statements), 1962-65 (Box 33, Folder 2)
    - Lessons in Love, 1962: script and cover text, typescripts, drafts, and notes (Box 33, Folder 3-4)
    - Helen Gurley Brown at Town Hall (script fragment?), 1966: (Box 33, Folder 5)
    - Lessons in Love, 1962, and Helen Gurley Brown at Town Hall, 1966: phonograph albums (Box 34)
  - Advertising copy
    - Correspondence (commentary on other's ads), 1971-81; 1991 (Box 35, Folder 1)
    - Copy, 1959, early, 1960s; 1994; undated (Box 35, Folder 2)
  - Radio spots (syndicated in Canada) (Box 35)
    [see SERIES III. SPEECHES AND APPEARANCES]
  - Television
    [see also SERIES III. SPEECHES AND APPEARANCES and SERIES V. COSMOPOLITAN]
    - Proposals: correspondence and drafts, early 1960s (Box 35, Folder 3-5)
    - Sitcom script, early, 1960s (Box 35, Folder 6)
  - Short pieces for other's works (forewords, contributions, school projects, quotes, blurbs, etc.): correspondence, writings, and publications including "Elizabeth Taylor's Passion," Somewhere Apart: My Favorite Place in Arkansas, and Teachers Make a Difference, 1976-99 (Box 35, Folder 7-9)
  - Autobiography/biography
    [See also Plays-Helen]
    - Offers to do biography: correspondence, 1980; 1988-89; 1996-2000 (Box 35, Folder 10)
    - Autobiographical work, unpublished
      - Drafts, 1962-63 (Box 35, Folder 11-18)
      - "Memories of My Mother and Early Life in Arkansas", late 1990s (Box 35, Folder 19)
      - Notes, March-April 1953 (Box 35, Folder 20)
      - Typescript, undated (Box 35, Folder 21)
      - Short stories and notes, 1944-74 (Box 35, Folder 22-23)
  - Plays/theatre
    - Correspondence, re: ideas, early, 1960s (Box 36, Folder 1)
    - Helen (biographical musical by Brown and Lyn Tornabene), 1970-71
      - Script (Box 36, Folder 2-3)
  - Magazine and newspaper (free-lance)
    - General (includes Lifeline proposal by Helen and David Brown, 1967, and Eye masthead, n.d.) (Box 36, Folder 4)
    - Articles, published and submitted: clippings, drafts, correspondence, and publications, 1956-2000; undated (Box 36, Folder 5-7)
    - Neue Illustrierte articles: drafts and correspondence, 1963-65 (Box 36, Folder 8)
    - TV Guide article, "How to Outfox New Breed of Macho Men": article and public response mail, 1986 (Box 36, Folder 9-10)
    - Letters to the editor: clippings and correspondence, 1977-80; 1986-89; 1996; undated (Box 36, Folder 11)
  - Poems, 1940, early 1960s (Box 36, Folder 12)
  - Fiction: short stories, notes, and fragments, circa 1940s-60 s? (Box 36, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous non-fiction pieces, 1963; undated (Box 36, Folder 14)
  - Notes and journals [?], circa, 1965-66; 1974; undated (Box 36, Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous projects (includes calendar and comic strip proposals), 1964; 1977; 2000 (Box 36, Folder 16)
  - David Brown, early, 1960s; 1975; 1980; 1985; 1987 (Box 36, Folder 17)
  - Audio recordings
    [These tapes have been digitized and are available to view online (Smith campus only)]
    - Series of taped interviews for "Helen" (biographical musical by Brown and Lyn Tornabene (9 tapes), 1970-71 (Box 36a)
    - Speech: "Helen Gurley Brown at Town Hall,", 1966 (?) (Box 36a)
- SERIES V. COSMOPOLITAN, 1965-2000
  Helen Gurley Brown's "child" for more than four decades was Cosmopolitan magazine. She changed a failing general interest magazine into a phenomenon-not only a best-selling magazine, but a cultural icon.
  This series comprehensively traces Brown's Cosmopolitan career from its beginnings to her final job evaluating Cosmopolitan's international editions. Of special note is the proposal circulated by David and Helen Brown for a new magazine, "Femme," that would become Cosmopolitan's new format.
  Throughout her tenure, a primary component of Brown's job was the courting of advertisers. Texts of the speeches and presentations she gave to advertisers and international editorial staff, as well as acceptance speeches for awards given to Cosmopolitan can be found in the subseries Advertising and publicity. This subseries includes advertisements for the magazine, including many written by Brown; promotional materials from the Hearst Corporation; and a large amount of newspaper clippings documenting coverage of Cosmopolitan in the press.
  Correspondence (the years 1988-89 are especially well documented) illuminates the day-to-day operations of Brown's editorial work, as letters flowed between Brown and writers, Cosmopolitan staffers, advertisers, and Hearst executives regarding specific issues of the magazine as well as ongoing concerns. Frequent correspondents among the staff and Hearst executives are filed by individual. Researchers interested in the advertising content of the magazine may wish to consult the letters of Stan Perkins and Seth Hoyt.
  The Editorial subseries provides an in-depth look at the magazine production process. Rules for writing and art format, which Brown enforced strictly, are compiled from the 1970s to the 90s. There are files of article ideas and editing memos, and a sample folder that represents the transformation of an article from its submitted state to the published version. Some notes on Brown's ideas for the magazine have been included, as is information on production and circulation. This subseries also contains the results of reader and staff surveys. Within the Editorial material is a section on special features. Material regarding the famous Burt Reynolds centerfold and other special issues of the magazine, such as anniversary issues and the last issue edited by Helen Gurley Brown, are filed here. Another special feature was the failed television pilot A View from Cosmo starring Brown. A "Best of" set of articles has Brown's favorite article among pieces from such regular Cosmopolitan writers as Erica Jong, Judith Krantz, and Gail Sheehy; a collection of some of Brown's long-running editorial, "Step into My Parlor;" and drafts and a copy of the only article Brown wrote for the magazine.
  A small subseries concerns Cosmopolitan Events and includes material from a lunch given by Brown for other women's magazine editors to raise awareness for the National Abortion Rights Action League and a party thrown by the Hearst organization to celebrate Brown's twenty-fifth anniversary as Editor.
  A set of Cosmopolitan magazines from 1953-79 is housed in the Sophia Smith Collection's Periodicals Collection.
  - Proposals
    - "Femme": prospectus, drafts, notes, and proposal, 1964-65 (Box 37, Folder 1-2)
    - Cosmopolitan, 1965 (Box 37, Folder 3)
  - Advertising and publicity
    - Advertising and sales presentations and award acceptances: speeches and notes (includes Henry Johnson Fisher award speech), 1973; 1978-96; undated (Box 37, Folder 4-9)
    - Lunch schedules, 1966-70 (Box 38, Folder 1)
    - New York Times advertisements: ads and copy (written by Brown), 1978-85; 1988-94 (Box 38, Folder 2-3)
    - Hearst promotional materials: general and press releases, 1965-2000 (Box 38, Folder 4-6)
    - Clippings
      - General, 1967-98; undated (Box 38, Folder 7)
      - Appointment as editor, 1965 (Box 38, Folder 8)
      - Early success of magazine, 1965-71 (Box 38, Folder 9)
      - Interviews with HGB re: Cosmopolitan, 1965; 1980; 1985; undated (Box 38, Folder 10)
      - Circulation and ad campaigns, 1970; 1978-93 (Box 38, Folder 11)
      - Events and appearances, 1982-95 (Box 38, Folder 12)
      - Anniversaries, 1985; 1990; 1995 (Box 38, Folder 13)
      - Specific covers and issues, 1972-95; undated (Box 38, Folder 14)
      - Excerpts from Cosmopolitan articles, 1985-86 (Box 38, Folder 15)
      - International editions, 1971-98 (Box 38, Folder 16)
      - Brown retirement, 1996; 2000 (Box 38, Folder 17)
      - Medill School of Journalism chair, 1985 (Box 38, Folder 18)
      - Compiled by Hearst, 1991; 1996-98 (Box 38, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence
    - Individuals
      - Bahrenburg, D. Claeys (President of Hearst Magazines), 1985-93 (Box 39, Folder 1)
      - Bennack, Frank (President and Chief Executive of Hearst Magazines), 1976-98; undated (Box 39, Folder 2)
      - Berlin, Richard (President and Chief Executive of Hearst Magazines), 1966-73 (Box 39, Folder 3)
      - Black, Cathleen (Publisher of Hearst Magazines), 1999-2000; undated (Box 39, Folder 4)
      - Boisriveaud, Juliette (Editor of Cosmopolitan France), 1974-76 (Box 39, Folder 5)
      - Carter, John Mack (Editor-in-Chief of Good Housekeeping and President of Hearst Magazines), 1975-94 (Box 39, Folder 6)
      - Deems, Richard (President of Hearst Magazines), (includes circulation figures), 1964-92; undated (Box 39, Folder 7)
      - DuPuy, Frank (Vice President and Publisher of Cosmopolitan), 1967-75 (Box 39, Folder 8)
      - Hoyt, Seth (West coast advertising agent), 1988-96 (Box 39, Folder 9)
      - McSharry, Diedre (Editor of Cosmopolitan U.K.), 1973-2000; undated (Box 39, Folder 10)
      - Mansfield, Terry (Managing Director of National Magazine Company Ltd. U.K.), 1988; 1999 (Box 39, Folder 11)
      - Maurer, Gil (President of Hearst Magazines) and Ann, 1975-99; undated (Box 39, Folder 12)
      - Meade, Walter (Managing Editor of Cosmopolitan ), 1974-96; undated (Box 39, Folder 13)
      - Miller, John (Executive Vice President of Hearst Corporation) and Bunny, 1965-76; 1982; 1988-90; undated (Box 39, Folder 14)
      - Miller, Mark and Linda, 1982; 1988-89; 1997 (Box 39, Folder 15)
      - Perkins, Stan (West coast advertising agent), 1975-82; 1988-89; 1996 (Box 39, Folder 16)
      - Porterfield, Lou (Vice President and Publisher of Cosmopolitan), 1978-89; 1996 (Box 39, Folder 17)
      - Letters from Roberta Ashley (Executive Editor of Cosmopolitan), re: quitting smoking, 1971-79 (Box 39, Folder 18)
    - General
      - 1966-86 (Box 39, Folder 19-21)
      - 1987-94 (Box 40, Folder 1-8)
      - 1995-2001, undated (Box 41, Folder 1)
    - Harvard Lampoon, 1972 (Box 41, Folder 2)
    - Medill School of Journalism (Hearst endowed professorship in Brown's name) from faculty and students, includes press releases, 1987-96 (Box 41, Folder 3)
    - Re: Brown's retirement, 1996-97 (Box 41, Folder 4-5)
  - Editorial
    - "Cosmo [format] explained"
      - General, 1965, late, 1970s; 1988-96; undated (Box 41, Folder 6-7)
      - Art and photography, 1967-72; undated (Box 41, Folder 8)
      - Editing and writing, 1967-71; 1980; 1994-96; undated (Box 41, Folder 9)
    - Article ideas, 1970s, mid, 1980s; undated (Box 41, Folder 10)
    - Article inventory, 1985 (Box 41, Folder 11)
    - Editing process (shows article from first submission to final publication), 1984-85 (Box 41, Folder 12)
    - Editing memos (includes article ideas and manuscript), 1969-80; 1988-89; undated (Box 42, Folder 1-5)
    - Covers, 1987-91 (Box 42, Folder 6)
    - Production schedules, 1985; 1987; 1997 (Box 42, Folder 7)
    - Circulation and miscellaneous statistics, 1968; 1973; 1986; 1989-96; undated (Box 42, Folder 8)
      [see also Correspondence: Richard Deems]
    - Surveys of readers and staff about magazine content (includes Brown's notes), 1987; 1989; 1992-93 (Box 42, Folder 9)
    - Brown's notes, 1969-71, late 1990s, n.d. (Box 42, Folder 10)
    - Threatened lawsuit, 1983-84 (Box 42, Folder 11)
    - Special issues/features
      - "Step into My Parlor,", 1965; 1970-72; undated (Box 43, Folder 1)
      - "Getting It," (only Cosmopolitan article Brown wrote): drafts and published article, 1994 (Box 43, Folder 2)
      - Centerfold issues: correspondence re: Burt Reynolds and issues of magazine (includes Reynolds and Arnold Schwarzenegger), 1972-80 (Box 43, Folder 3-5)
        [see also Events-Twenty-Fifth Anniversary and SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS-Photographs for John Davidson]
      - "Power" article: correspondence, quotes, and lists, 1981 (Box 43, Folder 6-7)
        [see also SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE-Individuals]
      - Television shows
        - Correspondence, includes contract, 1981-83; 1988-91; 1998 (Box 43, Folder 8)
        - A View from Cosmo: interview notes, biographies, schedules, and overview with Brown's notes, circa, 1983 (Box 43, Folder 9)
      - Twentieth anniversary, 1985 (Box 43, Folder 11)
      - Elizabeth Taylor interview, 1987
        - Correspondence (Box 44, Folder 1)
        - Cassette tape (Box 44, Folder 2)
        - Transcripts (Box 44, Folder 3)
        - Article and drafts (Box 44, Folder 4-5)
        - Clippings (Box 44, Folder 6)
        - Hunk poster, 1991-94 [?] (Box 44, Folder 8)
        - Last Brown issue: proposed Bill Clinton article correspondence, article ideas, plans, and final issue, 1996-97 (Box 44, Folder 9-10)
        - Miscellaneous, 1971 [?], 1987 (Box 44, Folder 11)
        - Clipped articles for proposed "best of" issues (includes Brown's favorite article), 1965-1978 (Box 44, Folder 12-13)
    - Events
      - NARAL lunch for editors of women's magazines: correspondence, lists of invitees/attendees, planning materials, research, and notes from presentation, 1986 (Box 45, Folder 1-3)
      - Twenty-fifth anniversary party, Jun, 1990
        - Invitations, attendees lists, and programs (Box 45, Folder 4)
          - Correspondence
            - Attendees: includes James Marlas, Mark Goodson, Diane von Furstenberg, Alexandra Mayes Birnbaum, Mort Zuckerman, Art Buchwald, Joy Philbin, Erica Jong, Mort Janklow, Peter Jennings, Iris Love, Beverly Sills, Liz Smith, Tina Brown, Barbara Walters, John Mack Carter, and Irving Lazar (Box 45, Folder 5)
            - Declined: includes Bill Blass, Connie Chung, Barry Diller, Farrah Fawcett, Hume Cronyn, Angela Lansbury, John Kluge, Jane Fonda, Liza Minelli, Kitty Carlisle Hart, Goldie Hawn, Christie Brinkley, Julio Iglesias, Jimmy Carter, Gloria Vanderbilt, Mia Farrow, and Joan Lunden (Box 45, Folder 6)
        - Memorabilia and clippings (Box 45, Folder 7-8)
      - Visitors to office: correspondence, biographies, and lists, 1973; 1979; 1988-94; undated (Box 45, Folder 9)
    - Early Cosmopolitans, 1887-1894, 1913, undated (incomplete) (Box 45, Folder 10-12)
    - Miscellany (Box 45, Folder 13)
- SERIES VI. OVERSIZE MATERIALS, 1965-96
  These items have been culled from other series for preservation purposes. The series features large photographs and artwork of Brown; an honorary degree; birthday cards and tributes; writings; publicity from her books and Cosmopolitan; material from Cosmopolitan; and scrapbooks from Sex and the Office, a television show proposal, a Cosmopolitan speech, and her Cosmopolitan twenty-fifth anniversary party.
  - Awards and tributes (includes honorary LLD from Woodbury University, birthday cards, and gold record from staff), 1985-88 (Box 46)
  - Interview (interview with Liz Smith), 1983 (Box 46)
  - Photographs and artwork, 1961-96 (Box 46)
  - Writings (Neue Illustrierte, Sex and the Single Girl and Sex and the Office posters and advertisements, and Having It All publicity), circa, 1963-64; 1982 (Box 46)
  - Cosmopolitan
    - Publicity (includes New York Times advertisements with copy by Brown, Hearst publicity), 1978-85; 1988-94 (Box 46)
    - Circulation statistics, 1973 (Box 46)
    - "Sample article" proofs, 1985 (Box 46)
    - Mock re-design, 1995 (Box 46)
  - Scrapbooks
    - Sex and the Office, 1964 (Box 47)
    - Portfolio promoting The Helen Gurley Brown Show, circa, 1971 (Box 47)
    - San Antonio speech, 1985 (Box 47)
    - Cosmopolitan 25th anniversary, 1990 (Box 47)
  - "Helen" clipboard (Box 47)
  - Cosmopolitan publicity and tributes from staff, 1985?; 1989-90 (Mapcase Flat File)
  - Cosmopolitan "hunk" posters, circa, 1990s (Mapcase Flat File)
  - Charcoal drawing of Brown, 1965 (Mapcase Flat File)
- "In Case of My Death" letter, personal and professional correspondence, Cosmopolitan, 1973; 1998-2002; 2002-08; Accession 2003-S-0012; .25 linear feet (1 container) (Box 1)
- Correspondence, The Late Show: typescript, 2001-2003; 1993; Accession 2004-S-0014; .25 linear feet (1 container) (Box 1)
- Addition, Accession 2004-S-0027 (Box 1)
  - Richard Heffner correspondence, 1983-2004 (Box 1)
  - Other correspondence, 2003-2004 (Box 1)
  - Book: Dear Pussycat - correspondence used in book (photocopies), 2004; 1966-1999 (Box 1)
  - Book: Dear Pussycat - typescript, 2003 (Box 1)
- Addition, Accession 2004-S-0039
  - Correspondence to mother (Cleo Bryan) and sister (Mary Alford), 1930-1989; 1970-1989 (Box 1, Box 2)
  - Correspondence to childhood friend, Elizabeth Jessup, 1930-1949; 1970-1999 (Box 1, Box 2)
  - Memorabilia - includes high school diploma, clippings, 1920-1969 (Box 1, Box 2)
  - Book: Dear Pussycat: Mash Notes and Missives from the Desk of Cosmopolitan's Legendary Editor - Copies of correspondence not used in book, 2004; 1990-2009 (Box 2)
  - Book: Dear Pussycat: Mash Notes and Missives from the Desk of Cosmopolitan's Legendary Editor - published book (Box 2)
- Addition, Accession 2004-S-0061
  - Book: Dear Pussycat - typescripts, correspondence and notes, 1983-2003 (Box 1)
  - Book: Dear Pussycat - published copy of book, 2004 (Box 1)
- Faux leopard fur hat and scarf, 2008; Accession 2008-S-0065 (Box 1)